Edward Julian Nally Papers, 1812-1953 (bulk 1905-1948): Finding Aid
Manuscripts Division
Edward Julian Nally Papers
1812-1953
1905-1948
Manuscripts Division
Nally, Edward Julian, 1859-1953.
C0251
13 boxes
4.25 linear feet
The personal papers of Edward Julian Nally, an American radio industrialist, trace the development of his career in the communications industry, from his earliest days with the Western Union Telegraph Co. (1875-1890), through his tenure with the Postal Telegraph Cable Co. (1890-1913), to his years with the Marconi Wireless Telegraph Co. of America (1913-1919); the bulk of the collection, however, covers his years with the Radio Corporation of America (RCA), for which he served as first president (1919-1923) and director.
Gift of Mrs. F.H. Nahn and her brother Julian Nally '27.
No appraisal information is available.
Collection is open for research use.
The collection contains personal papers of Nally which trace the development of his career in the communications industry. The collection includes correspondence, photographs, and printed matter from Nally's earliest days with the Western Union Telegraph Co. (1875-1890), through his tenure with the Postal Telegraph Cable Co. (1890-1913), to his years with the Marconi Wireless Telegraph Co. of America (1913-1919); the bulk of the collection, however, covers his years with the Radio Corporation of America (RCA), for which he served as first president (1919-1923) and director, providing insight into the growth of the company, from its nascent development to its world-wide communications empire. Technological developments in radio and television (color and "ultrafax") are described, and material about the company's radio show, "The Magic Key of R.C.A.," with a script for its 1939 New Year's gala, are included.
The collection also includes correspondence, photographs, memorials, and a scrapbook of Samuel Finley Breese Morse, inventor and painter, whose great-grandfather, Samuel Finley, was the fifth president of the College of New Jersey (Princeton). Among the papers are a daguerreotype of Morse likely made by Matthew Brady about 1850 and a genealogy of the Finley and Breese families written by Morse in 1841.
Nally was a communications executive, a pioneeer in telegraph, telephone, and radio. He started as a messenger boy (1875) in St. Louis with the Western Union Telegraph Company and became president of RCA in 1919.
Color television -- United States -- History.; Radio programs -- United States.; Radio -- United States -- History.; Telegraph, Wireless -- Marconi system.; Television -- United States -- History.; Ultrafax.; Correspondence.; Daguerreotypes.; Genealogies.; Photoprints.; Radio scripts.; Daguerreotypes (photographs).; American history/20th century; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872.; Marconi Wireless Telegraph Company of America.; Radio Corporation of America.; Western Union Telegraph Company.; Brady, Mathew B., approximately 1823-1896.
- Series 1: Biographical Material, dates not examined; 1 box
  Collection is open for research use.
  Consists of biographical material of Edward Julian Nally, including correspondence regarding Catholic Builders of the Nation, press releases, passports, and visas.
  Arranged by genre of material.
  - Addresses- Correspondence re: Catholic Builders of the Nation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Passports, Visas, etc., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Book Collection (Elbert Hubbard), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
- Series 2: Career, 1899-1929; 8 boxes
  Consists of papers related to Edward Julian Nally's career with telegraphs, including companies such as Western Union Telegraph, Postal Telegraph Cable Co., and Marconi Wireless Telegraph Company of America.
  This series is arranged into five subseries: Telegraph--Early Days, Western Union Telegraph, Postal Telegraph Cable Co., Marconi Wireless Telegraph Company of America, and Radio Corporations of America (R.C.A.).
  - Subseries 2A: Telegraph—Early Days, dates not examined; 1 box
    Consists of papers related to the early days of telegraph.
    Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.
    - Telegraph—Early Days, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2B: Western Union Telegraph, dates not examined; 1 box
    Consists of correspondence while at Western Union Telegraph.
    Arranged by genre of correspondence.
    - Correspondence, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - Correspondence (on leaving Western Union to enter service of Postal Telegraph Cable Co.), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2C: Postal Telegraph Cable Co., 1899-1902; 1 box
    Consists of correspondence while at Postal Telegraph Cable Co. as well as Saturday Evening Post articles.
    - Correspondence (on the occasion of appointment to assistant to General Superintendent, 1901; 2 folders (Folder 4-5)
    - Saturday Evening Post article, 1899; 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Saturday Evening Post article, 1902; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2D: Marconi Wireless Telegraph Company of America, 1913-1920; 2 boxes
    Consists of correspondence while at Marconi Wireless Telegraph Company of America.
    - Correspondence, 1913-1920; 2 boxes
      - Cummings, Homer S, 1918-1920; 1 folder (Folder 1)
      - 1919, 1 folder (Folder 2)
      - 1918, 1 folder (Folder 3)
      - 1917, 1 folder (Folder 4)
      - 1916, 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - 1915, 1 folder (Folder 6)
      - 1914, 1 folder (Folder 7)
      - 1913, 1 folder (Folder 8)
      - Congratulations on entering the service of American Marconi, 1913; 1 folder (Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous and printed matter, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
      - Marconi's Wireless Telegraph Co., Ltd. (British Marconi), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
      - re: Lee DeForest, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      - re: Roy A. Weagant, dates not examined; 1 box
        - The Life of Roy A. Weagant: by George H. Clark, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
        - Scrapbook, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
        - Miscellaneous pages, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - Radio: technical aspects, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
      - re: Early Beginnings of R.C.A., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2E: Radio Corporations of America (R.C.A.), 1919-1929; 5 boxes
    Consists of correspondence and papers regarding labor relations, the United States Navy, and technical developments in Radio, Television, and Ultrafax.
    Arranged by subject of correspondence.
    - Formative Years, 1919-1920; 1 box
      - Correspondence, 1919-1920: Election to the Presidency of R.C.A.- congratulations, 1 folder (Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1919: Formative Days of the New Corporation, 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, 1920-1925; 1 box
      - Miscellaneous, 1920; 1 folder (Folder 3)
      - Conferences with Godfrey Isaacs and other Europeans, 1920-1921; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      - 1921, 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - 1922: Europe and other subjects, 1 folder (Folder 6)
      - 1923, 1 folder (Folder 7)
      - 1924: Europe and South America, 1 folder (Folder 8)
      - 1924: Federal Trades Commission, 1 folder (Folder 9)
      - 1925: Europe and Other Subjects, 1 folder (Folder 10)
    - Labor Relations, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
    - Committee on Incentive Compensation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Subsidiaries, dates not examined; 1 box
      - Laboratories, undated; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      - Communications and Others, undated; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - United States Navy, dates not examined; 1 box
      - Personal and Semi-Official Communications, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      - Politics, Policies, and Politicians (Admiral Bullard), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - Alexanderson Alternator, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
      - History of Radio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Special Foreign Matters, 1929; 1 box
      - South American records and reports, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
      - Pan-American Wireless Telegram and Telephone Co., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      - All American Cables Inc., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
      - French Traffic Agreement, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      - C.R.I.C. (Commercial Radio International Committee), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - International Communications Conference, 1929; 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Technical Developments in Radio, Television, and Ultrafax, dates not examined; 1 box
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
      - Toscanini and the NBC Symphony Orchestra, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      - Testimony before Congress, re: "know North America", dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
      - Program Standards, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      - Policy re: Political Party Conventions, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - Excerpt from official report of proceedings before the F.C.C., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
      - Letter from President Harding, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
      - re: Histrory of Radio to 1926: Dean Gleason Archer, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
      - re: General Electric's station WGY, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
      - "The Magic Key of RCA": script, correspondence, press release, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
      - Television (black and white), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
      - Television (color), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
      - Ultrafax, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
    - Papers of Historical Signifigance, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - David Snarnoff, dates not examined; 1 box
      - Correspondence, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      - Photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
      - Press Releases, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      - Printed matter by or about David Snarnoff, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous material, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- Series 3: Photographs, dates not examined; 1 box
  Consists of photographs of Edward Julian Nally.
  - Photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
- Series 4: Miscellaneous Material, 1945-1947; 1 box
  Consists of miscellaneous correspondence, legal suits, financial matters, and technical developments.
  - Correspondence, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - "Daddy Nally", dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Legal Suits, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Financial matters, 1945-1947; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Technical Developments, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
- Series 5: Printed Matter, dates not examined; 1 box
  Consists of television and promotional material.
  - Miscellaneous, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Television, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Promotional Material, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
- Series 6: Papers of Others, 1850; 2 boxes
  Consists of some papers and clippings of Samuel Finley Breese Morse.
  - Morse, Samuel F. B, 1850; 1 box
    - Correspondence, 1850; 1 box
      - McNicol, D., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
      - Morse, Charles W. and Manetta, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
      - Morse, Jedediah, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
      - Morse, Lucretia Pickering (and journal), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      - Morse, Samuel F. B. (grandson), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      - Photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
      - Daguerretype, circa 1850; 1 folder (Folder 7)
        Likely by Matthew Brady. Original removed to high security vault, patrons are asked to reference the surrogate image provided.
      - Memorials, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
      - Genealogy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous Matterial, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
      - Printed Matter, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Morse, Samuel Finley Breese: bound volume of clippings, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
- 32101037104989 (Box 1)
- 32101037104997 (Box 2)
- 32101037105002 (Box 3)
- 32101037105010 (Box 4)
- 32101037105028 (Box 5)
- 32101037105036 (Box 6)
- 32101037105044 (Box 7)
- 32101037105051 (Box 8)
- 32101037105069 (Box 9)
- 32101037105077 (Box 10)
- 32101037105085 (Box 11)
- 32101037105093 (Box 12)
- 32101037105101 (Box 13)